Finding Aid for Graduate Employees Organization (University of Michigan) records, 1970-2015
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Graduate Employees Organization (University of Michigan) Records
1970-2015
1975-2005
Graduate Employees Organization (University of Michigan)
87134 Bimu F24 2
Legally-certified collective bargaining agent for the graduate student teaching and staff assistants at the University of Michigan. Includes minutes of meetings, announcements, newsletters and other materials concerning, in part, its activities to gain recognition and its strike against the University in 1975. Also includes material related to the organization's bargaining and negotiations with the University.
23.8 linear feet in 25 boxes
1.2 MB online
2 web sites online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor No. 7185 ) was received in four accessions: 1985, 1988, 1989, 1994 and 2004.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Graduate Employees Organization records are open for research use with the exception of s set of files subject to FERPA restrictions. Restricted files are located in boxes 13-16.
The Graduate Employees Organization (GEO) is the legally certified collective bargaining agent for the graduate student teaching and staff assistants (GSAs) at the University of Michigan. These GSAs concurrently pursue graduate degrees and teach undergraduates at the University of Michigan. As GEO tee-shirts note, they are "Workers, Teachers, Students." As the bargaining agent for GSAs, GEO has negotiated and sustained a series of contracts improving the conditions of employment since 1975. From the vantage point of GEO, this task was made considerably more difficult by an intransigent university administration, adverse Michigan Employment Relations Council (MERC) decisions, the 30% annual turnover of membership within GEO, and the burnout of unpaid officers. But GEO has endured and at present is the oldest, continually-functioning union of graduate student employees in the country. This longevity is owed to the periodic infusion of new blood, leaders newly committed to "carry it on" in the GEO tradition, and to the continued guidance and support of GEO's affiliates, the Michigan Federation of Teachers and the American Federation of Teachers.
After an unsuccessful attempt in 1971, GSAs were able to organize a union over the course of the 1973-74 academic year. This union, GEO, was sanctioned by a MERC certification election in April 1974. GEO then began the arduous process of reaching a contract settlement with the university. The first contract was ratified in March 1975 after a five week-strike by GEO. The second contract was tentatively agreed to in November 1976, but the university refused to sign it until GEO dropped pending grievances. GEO filed an unfair labor practice (ULP) suit against the university; the university countered that the ULP did not apply since GSAs were students, not teachers. This began a series of suits and appeals which ended with a 1981 MERC decision that teaching and staff assistants were employees, but research assistants (who had been part of GEO) were students. In November 1981, the 1976 contract was finally signed by both parties and ratified by the members.
The MERC decision of 1981 marked a watershed for GEO. No longer could the university profitably argue that GEO had no legal right to exist. The university changed the tenor of its bargaining, turning to maximizing productivity in relation to GSA costs. GEO continued to bargain for a fair wage, elimination of tuition for GSAs, control of class size, paid training for teaching assistants, and stronger language on affirmative action. These issues determined the nature of the negotiations and contracts of 1983, 1985, 1986, and 1987. While the bargaining was tense, the confrontations which marked the process in the 1970s were largely absent; only in 1987 did a strike seem possible.
Over the course of its history, GEO has prided itself on being a truly democratic union. Its constitution provides that any substantive decision has to be approved by a vote of the members. At times this has made for delay and difficulty in transacting union business, but the leaders regard this as a fair trade off. Originally the day-to-day business of GEO was carried out by the executive committee while the stewards council saw to the organizing and outreach functions of the union. In the early 1980s, the administration of GEO was reorganized to include more voices in guiding the union. At this time, a ten-member steering committee was formed to supplant the executive committee. The day-to-day running of the union has fallen to paid office staffers, drawn from the ranks of GSAs. Although not officially disbanded, the stewards council was dissolved, and met only at times of crisis. The council was reinstated in October of 1991 and continues to operate in much the same way as before the disbanding.
The GEO has continued to fight for the rights of graduate employees delving into issues of race discrimination, sexual harassment, and discrimination based on international student status. The group has also continued to be actively involved in the Ann Arbor community with activities such as Adopt-a-Store and the National Day of Action. Bargaining and negotiations continue to be important functions of the GEO, and issues such as childcare for GSIs and appropriate healthcare benefits have been topics of negotiation. The 2005 negotiations created a particularly broad set of documents, including ballots for a proposed strike.
The records of the Graduate Employees Organization consist of agendas and minutes of meetings, correspondence, newspaper clippings, newsletters, contract negotiating proposals and notes, and membership lists. These materials document the struggle of GSAs for recognition, fair wages, and good working conditions at the University of Michigan since 1974. The records of GEO came to the library in a series of accessions beginning in 1985. These accessions were arranged into five series: Administration, Bargaining, Office Files, Original Artwork, and Archived Website, reflecting the core structures and functions of the union. Some of the materials in different accessions overlap in dates and information with the prior accessions to this collection.
Subjects:
Graduate Employees Organization (University of Michigan); College teachers' unions--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Strikes and lockouts--College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Students.; Graduate teaching assistants--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Administration, 1971-2003
  The Administration series was created in the course of processing and consists of materials related to the structural organization of the union, its affiliation with MFT/AFT, and its efforts to keep members informed. This series is comprised subseries reflecting different accession of GEO records. Records within each subseries are alphabetically by type of material. The series as a whole reflects GEO's pragmatism and commitment to fairly representing the interests of its members. The researcher should note that decision-making within the GEO hierarchy was mutable with the executive committee, stewards council, and steering committee having final say at different times. The 1975 strike tactics and strategy are well covered in the minutes of the executive committee and stewards council and in The Picket Line, the GEO daily newsletter of spring 1975.
  - 1972-1989, primarily 1974-1989
    - Constitution, 1975-1988 (Box 1)
    - Histories, 1975-1985 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with Affiliates, 1975-1982
      - GEO-AFT (American Federation of Teachers) decision to affiliate, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - AFT Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - MFT (Michigan Federation of Teachers)
        - Conventions, 1975-1980; 5 folders (Box 1)
        - Correspondence, 1976-1982 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Meetings (and agendas), 1973-1989
      - Executive Committee, 1975-1980; 6 folders (Box 1)
      - Steering Committee (replaced Executive Committee), 1981-1989; 6 folders (Box 1)
      - Organization of Teaching Fellows (precursor of Stewards Council), 1973 (Box 1)
      - Stewards Council, 1974-1980; 1986; 8 folders (Box 1)
      - Membership, 1973-1986; 8 folders (Box 1)
      - Membership, 1981-1986; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Newsletters and Publications, 1974-1989
      - GEO Newsletter, 1974 (Box 2)
      - The Picket Line (daily) (strike newsletter), February 1975-March 1975 (Box 2)
      - GEO Gazette, May 1975-May 1980 (Box 2)
      - GEO Newsletter, 1982-1989 (Box 2)
    - Outreach (mass mailings, leaflets, fliers), 1973-1989; 9 folders (Box 2)
  - 1974-1987
    The Administrative Files, 1974-1987 subseries contain materials relating to the running of GEO as an organization, its history and some of its concerns. The documentation consists of correspondence, historical information, and printed materials, such as membership handbooks and flyers. The correspondence subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically. Also contained in this series are surveys done by GEO of other Big 10 universities and some interesting letters from disgruntled GEO members (Box 9).
    - Agency Shop
      - Correspondence (Box 9)
        - 1983/84-1986, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Enforcement, 1982-1985 (Box 9)
    - Background/Historical
      - Chronology, July 1974-August 1976 (Box 9)
      - Constitutional Amendments, 1985 (Box 9)
      - GSA Program, Pre-1975 (Box 9)
      - History of GEO Constitution, Bylaws & Elections, 1979; 1986 (Box 9)
      - Organization of Teaching Fellows, Minutes, Correspondence, 1973 (Box 9)
    - Committees
      - Election Committee, Returns, 1982/83 (Box 9)
      - Media Committee
        - Articles on UM Students & Faculty, 1975 (Box 9)
        - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 9)
        - Mailing List, 1986 (Box 9)
      - Negotiating Committee, Minutes, 9, August 1988 (Box 9)
      - Research Committee, Minutes, 7, February 1987 (Box 9)
      - Steering Committee
        - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 9)
        - Members, 1984/85 (Box 9)
        - Minutes, 1985/86-1986/87; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence
      - AAUP, 1975 (Box 9)
      - Center for Research on Learning & Teaching, 1984/85 (Box 9)
      - Departmental, 1975/76 (Box 9)
      - Drug Testing at UM, 1986/87 (Box 9)
      - General
        - 1975/76-1981, 5 folders (Box 9)
        - 1985 (Box 9)
      - Membership, 1984/85 (Box 9)
      - Michigan Education Assoc., 1975/76 (Box 9)
      - Michigan Federation of Teachers, 1974/75 (Box 9)
      - Nasty Letters, 1975 (Box 9)
      - Regents, 1976/77 (Box 9)
      - University of Michigan, 1984-86 (Box 9)
      - UM Administration, 1974-76 (Box 9)
    - Feminist Caucus, Letter to the Editor, 1975 (Box 9)
    - Publications
      - Flyers
        - Discrimination, 1974 (Box 9)
        - 1975, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - 1984/85 (Box 9)
      - Membership Handbooks, 1975/761978/79 1986-89 (Box 9)
      - Press Releases, 1975-1982; 1984; 1986; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Songs (Box 9)
    - Stewards' Council
      - Attendance list, October 1975 (Box 9)
      - Correspondence
        - 1983/84 (Box 9)
        - 1986 (Box 9)
      - Distribution Network, 1984 (Box 9)
      - Form Letters to Delinquent Stewards (Box 9)
      - Minutes
        - 9 March, 1982 (Box 9)
        - 1986 (Box 9)
      - Phone Chain, 1974-79, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Topical
      - Anniversary, 1989 (Box 9)
      - Big 10 Schools
        - GSA Policies, 1974 (Box 9)
        - Graduate Students Organizations (Box 9)
        - Survey
          - 1987-1988, 1990/91; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Foreign Students Regulations for Joining GEO (Box 9)
      - Foreign TA's, 1986 (Box 9)
      - Legislative Lobbying, 1980 (Box 9)
      - Membership
        - Membership Information System Proposal, 1975 (Box 9)
        - Membership List (Box 9)
      - Michigan State University Organizing Project
        - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 9)
        - Newspaper Clippings, 1988 (Box 9)
        - TA Survey, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Outreach (Box 9)
      - Resignations from GEO (Box 9)
      - TA's at UM, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Taxes
        - Correspondence
          - Attorneys, 1988 (Box 9)
          - Congress, 1988 (Box 9)
          - UM, 1988 (Box 9)
        - TA's Tax Situation, 1986-88 (Box 9)
        - Tax on Tuition Waivers
          - 1978-81, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Tuition Payment Program, 1978/79; 1982/83; 1985/86 (Box 9)
      - Tuition Rates, 1965-1987 (Box 9)
      - Tuition Waivers, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Tuition Waiver Policy Survey, 1986 (Box 9)
      - UM Budget Crisis, 1980 (Box 9)
      - Workshops
        - Stayin' Alive Conference, 1981 (Box 9)
        - TA Training & Sensitivity, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Work Study
        - TA's, 1980/81 (Box 9)
        - UM Program, 1987 (Box 9)
  - 1971-1985
    The Administrative Files, 1971-1993 contain information that relates mostly to GEO's constitution, its drafts and amendments, from 1975 to 1985. There are also background materials that supplement information found in the previous accession. A chronology of GEO's development from 1971 to 1976 is included in this series. (Box 11)
    - Background/Historical
      - Chronology, 1971-76 (Box 11)
      - Paper on GEO at UM, 1979 (Box 11)
    - Constitution
      - Amended and Revised Constitutions, 1975; 1978; 1981; 1985 (Box 11)
      - Amendments
        - 1978, 1979 (Box 11)
        - 1981 (Box 11)
      - Bylaws, 1986 (Box 11)
      - Proposed Amendments (Box 11)
      - Proposed Constitution (not ratified), 1975 (Box 11)
      - Proposed Constitutional Revisions, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Draft Statement of Issues Concerning GEO, 1980 (Box 11)
    - GEO Newsletter, November 1990; February 1993 (Box 11)
    - GEO Representatives to Departments, 1975 (Box 11)
    - Guidelines for Research on GEO (Box 11)
    - Phone Chains, 1992 (Box 11)
    - UM Budgetary Policy, 1980/81 (Box 11)
  - 1975-2003
    The Administrative Files, 1975-2003 contain materials relating to the running of the GEO as an organization, its history and its concerns. These records include correspondence, committee proceedings, other affiliate unions, and publications. Also covered by this series is the celebration of the organization's 25th Anniversary in 2000. (Box 15)
    - University of Michigan Lists of GSTA/GSSAs Appointments
      - February 1993 (Box 13)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2083 ]
      - March 1993 (Box 13)
      - June 1993 (Box 13)
      - October 1993 (Box 14)
      - November 1993 (Box 14)
    - Budget, 1991 (Box 15)
      [Restricted until July 1 2083 ]
    - Committees
      - Committee Descriptions, 1996 (Box 15)
      - Constitutional Committee, 2001 (Box 15)
      - Finance Committee, 2001 (Box 15)
      - Press Committee, 1995 (Box 15)
        (includes press package)
      - Sexual Harassment Concerns Committee, 1997 (Box 15)
      - Steering Committee, 1990-1997; 9 folders (Box 15)
      - Stewards' Council
        - Handbooks
          - Grievance Handbook, 1992 (Box 15)
          - Stewards Handbooks, 1993; 1999 (Box 15)
        - Meetings, 2000; 2001; 2002 (Box 15)
        - President's Report, 1994-1995 (Box 15)
        - Retreats, 1995; 1996; 1997; 2002; 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 15)
    - Dues Schedule, 1999-2000 (Box 15)
    - Employee Log Sheet, 1994 (Box 15)
    - GEO Affiliate Unions
      - General Information, undated (Box 15)
      - AFL-CIO Numbers That Count, Manual on Internal Organizing, 1988 (Box 15)
      - Alliance of Graduate Employee Locals (AGEL) Conference, 1999 (Box 15)
      - American Federation of Teachers (AFT)
        - Background Material, undated (Box 15)
        - AFT Award to Jon Curtiss, 1996 (Box 15)
      - Michigan Federation of Teachers (MFT)
        - Constitution and By-Laws, 1999; 2001 (Box 15)
        - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 15)
        - Financial Statements, 2002 (Box 15)
        - Minutes, 2000 (Box 15)
    - GEO Handbooks, 1996-1997; 1998-1999 (Box 15)
    - History, 2004 (Box 15)
      (website)
    - Membership Lists
      - 1994-1995 (Box 15)
      - 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - 2002, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Membership Meetings, 1994-2003; 8 folders (Box 15)
    - Membership Orientation, 1995; 1998; 1999 (Box 15)
    - National Day of Action, 1997 (Box 15)
    - Phone Scripts, 2002-2003 (Box 15)
    - Photographs
      - 1975 (Box 15)
      - 1990s undated (Box 15)
      - Child Care Issue, 2001 (Box 15)
      - Member Polaroids, undated (Box 15)
    - Publications
      - Brochure, 1993 (Box 16)
      - GEO Academic Planners, 1999; 2003 (Box 16)
      - GEO Newsletters, 2000 (Box 16)
        (scattered)
      - Original Art Work, undated (Box 16)
      - Quote File, 2000 (Box 16)
      - "Why Join GEO?", 1990 (Box 16)
    - Surveys, 1990-1998 (Box 16)
    - 25th GEO Anniversary, 1975-2000
      - Anniversary Flyer, 2000 (Box 16)
      - "Collective Bargaining in Higher Education", Silver Anniversary, 1997 (Box 16)
      - "Collective Bargaining", WSU Labor Studies, 1997 (Box 16)
    - Workshop for TAs, 1995 (Box 16)
  - 1986-2006
    The Administrative files (3.5 linear feet) include materials related to the running and activities of the GEO. These records include correspondence, community involvement projects, and leadership plans. Files are arranged in alphabetical order and then by date. A highlight is the grievance management cases (see Box 19) focusing on affirmative action, sexual harassment, and international graduate employees.
    - Correspondence
      - 1987-2000, 11 folders (Box 18)
      - Other College Campuses, 1993-1997; 3 folders (Box 18)
        (Regarding union organizing on those campuses)
      - Social Correspondence, 1993-2000 (Box 18)
        (Regarding potential event participation)
    - Department Interactions
      - English, 1990 (Box 18)
      - Organizing, 1991 (Box 18)
      - Departments, 1993 (Box 18)
      - Organizing, 1993-1994 (Box 18)
      - Organizing, 1995 (Box 18)
      - Department Specific, 1994-2000 (Box 18)
      - Ecology Department, 1990-1992 (Box 18)
      - Department Meeting, Undated (Box 18)
    - Events and Community Involvement
      - Adopt-a-Store, 1991-1992; 7 folders (Box 18)
      - Banner Action, 1992 (Box 18)
      - T-shirt, 1992 (Box 18)
      - Walkathon, 1993 (Box 18)
      - Workshops, 1993 (Box 18)
      - Fall Events, 1993 (Box 18)
      - Political Endorsements, 1994 (Box 18)
      - Newspaper Strike, 1995 (Box 18)
      - All Campus Labor Council, 1995-1996 (Box 18)
      - National Day of Action, 1996 (Box 18)
      - Affirmative Action, 1996-1998 (Box 18)
      - Affirmative Action, 1997 (Box 18)
      - Affirmative Action Focus Group, 1997-1998 (Box 18)
      - National Day of Action, 1997; 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Bash, 1997 (Box 18)
      - Health Care, 1997-2000 (Box 18)
      - GEO Bash, 1998 (Box 18)
      - Student Labor Action Coalition(SLAC), 1998 (Box 18)
      - UM Childcare, 1998-2001 (Box 18)
      - GEO Orientation, 1999 (Box 18)
      - Politics, 1999-2000 (Box 18)
      - Civil Rights and Social Justice, 2000 (Box 18)
      - General Grad Union Solidarity, 2001 (Box 18)
      - Committee on Student-Parent Issues (COSPI), 2004 (Box 18)
      - North Campus Housing, 2004 (Box 18)
    - Financial Records
      - Tax Assessments, 1987-1990; 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Tuition Assessment Letters, 1990 (Box 19)
      - Department Financial Support, 1990 (Box 19)
      - Tuition Concerns, 1990-1991 (Box 19)
      - UM Budget, 1991 (Box 19)
      - UM Budget Explanations, 1991-1993 (Box 19)
      - Treasurer Handbook, 1994-1997 (Box 19)
      - Tuition Assessment, 1996 (Box 19)
      - Financial Schedule, 1998-2005; 8 items (Box 19)
      - UM Funding Sources, 1999 (Box 19)
      - Bottom Line Budgeting, 2000-2001; 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Budgeting, 2002-2003 (Box 19)
      - Dues, 2003 (Box 19)
    - Grievance Management
      - International Graduate Student Instructor Training Materials (IGSI), 1995-1999; 2 folders (Box 19)
      - IGSI Insurance, 1995-1997 (Box 19)
      - IGSI Grievance, 1995-1999 (Box 19)
      - IGSI Info, 2004-2005; 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Michigan Daily with IGSI article, 2006 (Box 19)
      - Research -- TAs of Color, 1990-1994; 5 folders (Box 19)
      - TAs of Color, 1992-1998 (Box 19)
      - Sexual Harassment, 1996 (Box 19)
      - Grievance Management, 1990s (Box 19)
      - Psychology Interns, 1994-1996; 2 folders (Box 19)
      - ULA, 1998-2000 (Box 19)
    - Membership
      - Membership Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1993-1994 (Box 19)
      - Membership Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1992-1994 (Box 19)
      - Membership Meeting, 1999 (Box 19)
      - Membership Meeting, 2000 (Box 19)
      - Membership Lists, 2000 (Box 25)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2075 ]
      - Membership Revocation, 1991 (Box 25)
        [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2066 ]
      - Input, 1991-2005 (Box 19)
        - Surveys, 1991 (Box 19)
        - Testimonials, 1995-1997 (Box 19)
        - Organizational Surveys, 1995 (Box 19)
        - Pedagogy Surveys, 1998 (Box 19)
        - Debriefs, 2005 (Box 19)
        - Membership Feedback, 2003 (Box 19)
        - Note Box, undated (Box 19)
        - Parents Survey, 2004 (Box 19)
        - Membership Feedback Form, 2005 (Box 19)
    - Organization Activity
      - History Timeline, undated (Box 20)
      - GEO Handbook, 1986-1999 (Box 20)
      - Group Organizing, 1993 (Box 20)
      - GEO Office Manuel, 1996 (Box 20)
      - "Carry it on" Officers Handbook, 1993; 1997 (Box 20)
      - Calendar Advertising, 1995-1996 (Box 20)
      - Calendar Content, 1995-2000; 3 folders (Box 20)
      - Treasurer Planners, 1995-1998 (Box 20)
      - Organization Information, 1995-1998 (Box 20)
      - GEO History, 1995-1999 (Box 20)
      - Handbook Discussion, 1996 (Box 20)
      - Strike Planning, 1996 (Box 20)
      - Calendar, 1997 (Box 20)
      - Collective Bargaining Guide, 1997 (Box 20)
      - Carry It On, 1997 (Box 20)
      - Pedagogy Committee
        - Newsletters and Correspondence, 1997 (Box 20)
        - Newsletter, 1997; .ZIP File
      - Internal Organizing, Late, 1990s; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Advice and Organizing Tips, 1998 (Box 20)
    - Organization Activity (cont.)
      - Corporate Governance at UM, 1999-2000 (Box 20)
      - Organizing Materials, 2000 (Box 20)
      - JARC Reports, 2000 (Box 20)
      - Organizational Notes, 2004 (Box 20)
      - Governance, 2004 (Box 20)
      - Training Materials, 2005 (Box 20)
    - Other Organizations
      - NAGPS, 1988-1992 (Box 20)
      - Other Campuses, 1990s (Box 20)
      - TA Unions Conference, 1992 (Box 20)
      - AGEL Correspondence, 1997 (Box 20)
      - AGEL/AFT Info, 1995-1999; 3 folders (Box 20)
      - MFT, 1998-2000 (Box 20)
      - LEO Information, 2000 (Box 20)
      - LEO UM Web Information, 2001-2002 (Box 20)
      - LEO Solidarity, 2002 (Box 20)
      - LEO Communications, 2002 (Box 20)
      - LEO UM Union, 2003 (Box 20)
      - ELI, 2004 (Box 20)
    - Outreach and Publicity
      - Undergraduate Outreach, Undated (Box 20)
      - Press Release, 1989 (Box 20)
      - Advertising, 1990s (Box 20)
      - Publicity Projects, 1990s (Box 20)
      - Walkout Publicity, 1990s (Box 20)
      - Leaflets, 1990 (Box 20)
      - Coalition Building and Community Outreach, 1992 (Box 20)
      - Press List, 1992 (Box 20)
      - Outreach -- Meijer's Workers, 1994 (Box 20)
      - Detroit Free Press, 1995 (Box 20)
      - Press, 1996 (Box 20)
      - Advertising, 1997 (Box 20)
      - The Graduate Worker Newsletter, 1998 (Box 20)
      - Faculty Outreach, 1998-1999 (Box 20)
      - Undergraduate Outreach, 1998-1999 (Box 20)